Hey, guys. My name is The Cherno and welcome back to my C++ series.
This is going to be a really quick episode in which I'm just going to based answer the question
What is the difference between a struct and a class in C++?
The last time we talked about classes in General
And we had a bit of a basic introduction to what classes actually were you guys haven't seen that video check it out
There'll be a link to the description below as well as like some kind of weird annotation
I think what are they called cards? They'll be a card somewhere on the screen
but basically we have these two terms in C++, a struct which is short for structure or a class and
They might appear to be sort of similar and a lot of people are a little bit confused about what the differences are exactly
When you should be using a struct when you should be using a class this video is going to address all that so the difference
is this
There is basically none
There is one small difference to do with visibility so last time when I talked about
How we had a class having its members private by default which meant that if I was to do something like this
however
I did not
Declare this as public
Then we would get an error because you can see that it would tell us that the move method in the player class is
Inaccessible because it's been marked as private as default meaning only other methods inside this class can actually access that move method
Which is why we have to write public here if we want to execute this code because of course we're calling player
dot move outside of the player class and that's essentially where the difference comes in a
A Class is private by default
So if you don't specify any kind of visibility modifier like I did here if you don't just get rid of it
And you don't specify anything at all the default is
Private however was the struct the default is public that is the only difference between a struct and a class
Technically and you can see over here in our code we get an error because again move is inaccessible
However, if I change this to say struct player that's literally I just changed the word class to struct. That's all I've done
This is all fine now, and if I actually did want something to be private
I would explicitly have to write
Private and then of course that takes us back to the same error that we got with a class that is the difference
It's incredibly simple
That's really all there is to it however instead of just putting up a two-minute video and
just mentioning that I want to kind of talk about how we might be defining differences between those two words because
Like they might not technically have much of a difference however the usage in code is actually going to differ
the only reason struct really even exists in C++
Is because of the backwards compatibility that it wants to maintain with C, because code doesn't have classes
It does have structures though, and if we were suddenly to wipe out this whole struct Keyword
Entirely then we would lose all
compatibility because
The compilers the C++ compiler wouldn't know what struct was of course you could fix that pretty easily by just using a hash to find
So we could write something like hash Define struct class, right?
And then suddenly what that's going to do is replace all of our structs with classes
So in this case even if code might look pretty
Pretty simple if I compile it, you can see suddenly we get that same error telling us
move can't be accessed inside a class even though we've used the word struct here, because of course it's replaced
struct with the word class and then maybe yes
You can get that kind of compatibility between C code and C++
code back because ideally you should be able to go into C
code and replace the works struct with class and then make it public
And then that would be it that would be the end that there would be no more difference in that actual scenario
so then the difference kind of semantically
And how people see it come down to more or less the usage if there is no difference
when do I use struct versus class? Do I use a struct if I want all of my members to be public and I don't
want to have to write the word public is it really that
trivial? and yes by the way
It is actually that trivial and so because of that
People have kind of come up with their own
Definitions for what I think a struct should be and what I think a class should be, however
There is no really like there really is no like right or wrong answer
It's kind of up to your style of programming so since this is my video
Let's talk a little bit about my style of programming and where I might use each type
So I like to use struct whenever possible when I'm basically talking about plain old data or pod basically where I'm talking about
some kind of structure which just
represents variables a bunch of variables
And that's really all it's there for. A great example of this might be something like a mathematical
Vector class if I were to come over here
And I wanted to make some kind of structure which just held two floats together such as a Vec2 I
might define it as a struct and just have my x and y floats why because
fundamentally this Vec2 class or struct or whatever you want to call it, this Vec2 structure is just a representation of
Two floats that's what it is at its core
It's not supposed to really contain a massive amount of functionality like a player class might where it might be?
Having it might like a player class might have a 3D model
It might handle all the rendering code for that 3D model
It might be handling like how the player moves around the map and taking in keyboard input and all of that
There's just so much functionality there right whereas what this is. It's just two variables and we've grouped them
literally just for the reason of
Making our code easier to use that's all that we've done and of course that's not to say that
I'm not going to be adding methods to this
I absolutely
Will I
might add a method called add which takes in another Vec2 and then adds it to the current vector by doing something like
this right, but again what I'm doing here is I'm just
Manipulating these variables I've just added a function that will manipulate those variables, but at the end of the day
I'm still just talking about those two variables now of course if you were really to break it down and think about it
Really hard, then you could argue that
At the end of the day even the player class is just manipulating those variables however
There's a bit of a difference in terms of design
Because we're talking about something that is massively massively more complicated the other scenario is inheritance. I
will never use inheritance with structs if
If I get to the point where I'm actually going to have an entire class hierarchy or some kind of inheritance Hierarchy
I'm going to use a class for that because again
Inheritance is something that's adding another level of complexity and I just want my structures to be structures of data
That's it and additionally to that if you try and mix those
For example you have a class called A and then a struct called B
Which inherits from A, some compilers will give you warning telling you that you're inheriting from a class
But you're a struct and there are some other kind of minor differences, but again they're just warnings technically your code will still work
it's just a bit of a semantical difference, so those are kind of my
reasons for using a struct versus a class if I just want to represent
some Data in a structure
I will use a struct
but if I've got an entire class filled with functionality
Like a like a game world or a player or something that additionally might have inheritance and all of these all these systems
I'm going to use a class and again. That's how I personally differentiate between those two types
That's how a lot of people I've seen in the industry
differentiate between those two types, but again if
There is technically no difference apart from that visibility you can use a struct wherever you can use class that
They're going to work the same way
hope you guys enjoyed this video if you did please hit that like button of course you can follow me as well on Twitter and
Instagram
Links will be in the description below if you really like these videos and you want to support this series and see more
then you can support me on patreon.com/thecherno
And additionally to just supporting me and making sure that I can make more videos
You'll get access to early drafts as well as a discussion board where we talk about what actually goes into these videos
So if your interested in that check out the link in the description below
patreon.com/thecherno And next time we're going to continue on our journey
As to what classes are going to talk about stuff like
Inheritance and look at some examples of existing code to see how you should be structuring your classes
How you should be writing them and how we can use them in our code. I'll see you guys next time goodbye